Another tool that's very handy when you're working with a coated breed dog is scissors.
Lot of different types of scissors.
I'm going to show you 2 types.
This is just your straight regular scissors.
It's actually a straight blade.
It's a relatively straight blade in this type of scissor.
Depending on what you're comfortable working with, you can get longer bladed scissors.
You want to make sure that when you're picking out your scissors you try a bunch of different pair and make sure that the action is comfortable and smooth.
This a nice pair of scissors.
These scissors are probably 30 years old.
Make sure that the scissors are balanced and comfortable in your hand.
These scissors can be used for trimming around the eyes, trimming around the face, trimming around the feet.
It's important that you've got a comfortable pair that's manageable in your hand.
They do make left handed scissors.
Again, I'm left handed, but I've learned to do everything with right hand.
For those of you who are left handed and really need to be left handed, they do make left handed scissors and so you can find them.
Another pair of scissors we've got here are the thinning shears.
Again, you want to get a pair that is comfortable in your hand.
There's many different types.
This type of thinning shear has the tines cut into the blade on one side and the other side as you can see, is just the blade; it's flat.
You can use on different parts of the dog.
Again, when you're working around the face, working on the feet.
You would really have no reason to cut the body hair, but if you are not showing your dog and you do want to trim up some of it then this would give you a more natural look than if you just used the straight shears, which would just cut a blunt end.
Most dog breeds when you're showing them should not be scissored.
It happens, but they shouldn't be.
If you've got a dog at home and you just want to trim some of the coat off, then scissors can be very handy to use.
Important when you're getting scissors, make sure they're comfortable in your hands, that the blade is a good quality and you can get them sharpened.
Depending on how much you use them, you ought to get them sharpened about once a year.
You don't want to be pulling or breaking the dog's coat when you're using them on the coat.